at these these these factories will not
be able to compete unless they they move
towards you know greater and greater
automation. So and you think about you
start looking at all all the jobs that
are currently out there and if we think
about the robots and the AIs how many
are likely to feel this competitive
pressure almost all of them
>> almost all of them. So to say 25% is
absurd. The only thing I think that's
that that's slowing down this transition
is because AI capabilities they're still
not they're still very narrow in their
intelligence. They're not generalized
right? So they difficulty moving from
STEM as we talked about to other fields.
But as we get closer and closer to
artificial general intelligence and they
become their their intelligence becomes
more and more general, meaning they're
having PhD keep building in even more
domains, you're going to start to see
them move more and more to white collar
work. And as the AI start to get um as
we I mean there's a big manufacturing
challenge right now with robots, right?
But as as the AI more and more AI get
released into the world and they start
learning from interacting with the
environment again like children, they're
going to get better at navigating this
environment. We're already seeing like
Teslas and autopilot, right? Capable of
amazing things. And so really we just
have this manufacturing bottleneck. the
AI will be there in the next year or
two. They they'll be fairly generalized,
I think, to be able to work in most
environments. You're going to see those
robots just just flood the market. So, I
mean, I think realistically in the
horizon of 10 years, um you could look
at 80 and 90% of GDP economy jobs just
being gone.
[Music]
>> Good morning, Matthew.
>> Good morning. Um so today what what I
want to do in this conversation with you
is break down for our audience um what
AI is, what artificial intelligence is
um to start to unpack that and to
understand then what Catholic AI is and
why it's important and and the mission
of course of Magisterium AI and
everything that we're doing at
Longbeard.
>> Cool. Shoot.
>> Um so Matthew, let's start from the very
beginning then. What is artificial
intelligence? This is something that of
course is, you know, the buzzword of of
this summer of of of our time. Um there
feels like there's not a single
technology company that's not you know
working on AI as we speak. Um what is
it?
>> So there's a bunch of ways to define
what AI is. The definition I find the
most kind of useful is think of it as
kind of humanity's quest to replicate
the ability to think learn and know in
machines essentially thinking machines
is is essentially what we're trying to
create with artificial intelligence. And
in terms of thinking like thinking has
many components. There's the the
reflective aspect of it. There's the
critical you know the critical
analytical you know response to it.
There's in some sense there's that
self-awareness or that selfreflection.
Um are are machines doing that or are
they simulating or mimicking the the act
of thinking?
>> Yeah that's a good question and it's
it's a it's um it's pretty uh there's a
lot of debate around this. I mean I
wouldn't say that machines are thinking
in the same way we are.
Certainly I I would I would say that
they have the ability to to perform
certain kind of reasoning functions in a
sense they're able to take like a large
trough of data and you ask you know
query they're able to kind of distill
it. So you know we do this obviously uh
human beings do this as well. Um they um
I think they also have the ability that
we're seeing more and more that they
have the ability to kind of reflect and
they have this ability to kind of think
in in the kind of conceptual space. So
this is something kind of like new
because when they first came out I think
we just kind of you know thought of them
as we as we say you know scotasic
parrots basically where they're just
kind of paring um you know we we train
them on next token u prediction which
you know basically the way a large
language model works this might be
helpful for kind of kind of illustrating
the point is essentially when you submit
a prompt the AI is basically taking that
prompt and it's predicting what token
should follow after your prompt right
and a token is like a subword word unit.
Um, and so it basically kind of
calculates a distribution of what what
would be the what should be the probable
next token basically off off all all
probable words. It runs those it runs
the numbers and then it it basically
predicts what it thinks should be the
next token and it predicts that token
and then then it basically feeds that
token back into the input along with the
prompt and the previous token and then
it runs it again right and then it does
it again again and that that's basically
when you see it kind of generate word at
word that's essentially what it's doing.
>> So and for a long time we thought that's
all it was doing. It was just simply
calculating, you know, probabilities uh
based based on the distribution of all
possible words. But we're starting to
realize now as these models get more
intelligent and I I say that in
quotation marks, there's more going on
there that they're not just doing next
token prediction that they they there is
some kind of when you we train these
things and kind of we call the you know
the pre-training phase. We basically
give them access to whole troughs of
data and uh and they basically just you
know if they crunch it um so to speak
they do develop some conceptual
understanding of the way the you know
the world kind of works based upon the
data that they have access to. So and
and and so they do kind of um think and
and reason in a conceptual space or like
a latent space like we do. So this is
pretty interesting, right? So this this
is this is something beyond just next
token prediction that's happening here.
um they're they're able to actually
think ahead to some extent and this is
just this is really just more cutting
edge research coming out of anthropic
which is they're finally being able to
kind of prove this.
>> So um certainly you know what they're
doing is not what we're doing but it's
it's similar. So I it's kind of like
like an alien intelligence and and and
if you look into groups like Enthropic
and the research they're doing on on
mechanic mechanistic interpability it's
fascinating. you can kind of see how how
they think like even how they approach a
math problem, right? Um it's pretty
interesting. They they kind of have
parallel approaches where you know they
may take a quick pass at it and kind of
arrive at what they kind of think is
probably the right answer and then
they'll actually kind of also go through
and do it kind of very meticulously kind
of work through the actual math, right?
and they kind of see if if that initial
kind of run at it um which which arrived
at an answer after having kind of you
know done a little bit more of a kind of
a detailed you know thought processes
arriving u do they arrive at the same
answer right so this is pretty
interesting right I mean I don't think
that we we suppose in some ways you
could say that we do this I mean you
know someone asks us math questions we
may kind of instinctively have an idea
of what the answer should be but we
still have to kind of you know do the
math in our head to arrive there so in
some ways that what they're doing is is
the same but just seeing seeing how they
actually arrive there is is very
different So, so um
>> and Matthew is this ability for them to
to arrive at certain answers like this
is it very you know is it well
structured and and successful at certain
types of problems but maybe less
successful at others like for example
mathematics or something that have you
know I don't want to say simple but a
but a definable language a definable
mode of expression versus something like
a creative field or or something like
that which might you know require
certain aspects of the human experience
to to do very successfully. I mean I
mean I mean totally they're um they're
certainly better. I mean what they're
good at it's really it comes down to
what they're trained on. So the thing is
with with the STEM fields so science,
technology, um engineering, mathematics,
they they tend to excel in those fields
namely because they're we call their
kind of the verifiable domains, right?
So we're able to kind of feed them
problems and answers and it's very cut
cut and dry, right?
um and and because um they're verifiable
domains, we can actually um you know
train them a large corpus of data and
then feed them the problems and then we
and then when they come up with an
answer, we can verify that that answer
is correct. And so this is really
important especially because in the past
one of the one of the kind of major
bottlenecks in on AI development is is
is the fact that we have to kind of come
up with these problems and these
solutions, right? Um and uh and that's
very tedious because you know humans
have to propose propose the question and
the answer and there's you know so much
so much time and energy we have to do
that there's actually right now what the
problem is we we fed them all the the
problems and the answers that we have
access to um but we want them to go
beyond that and so um but but
essentially if you can think about
verifiable domains as as as being kind
of that unlock which allows these these
AIs to become you know excellent these
respective you know fields um in the
same way in the arts in the humanities
ities. Well, there those are not
verifiable domains, right? There is, you
know, if you ask someone like a some
kind of artistic question, do you like
this painting or don't you? Like what is
good about this painting? What is not? I
mean, that it's not like verifiable in
the same way like a math problem is,
right? It's much more subjective. And
so, so they tend not to be as good in in
those fields. I mean, they they memorize
a lot of, you know, all this information
is kind of uh compressed inside of their
parameters. So they they memorize what
people say about these things and and
they can parrot those backs, but they
but they don't they can't um provide
insight um in the same way they can with
math problems. They can't they can't be
sure that they're right and they can't
explain how they arrive there, right?
Because it's as I said, it's a more
subjective field. And so in those
domains, uh AI progress is much slower.
But I I think there is I should say in
the area of code as well. The nice thing
about like math and code, uh, they're
excellent for teaching machines kind of
how to think and reason, right? How to
think step by step, so so to speak. And
the learning that they do in these, um,
kind of STEM fields, it does actually
have relevance in the non non- STEM
fields, right? I mean, there's a lot of
obviously the philosophical reasoning
for instance,
>> um, you know, it philosophical reasoning
is typically um, uh, done in like, you
know, the typical uh, language, right?
Uh, not not in mathematical terms. Um
but but so what the AIS learn in math
and coding they can kind of apply
semantically right in philos exactly so
it can help them with philosophical
reasoning and and uh what we've been
observing as well is it also makes them
uh pretty good at even understanding
theological reasoning and so I think
that's so the breakthroughs they're
making in STEM will have I think uh
implications for for many other fields
although you know that they're not going
to have as much rapid progress in in the
arts and the humanities as they will in
STEM.
>> Wow. And Matthew, in terms of reasoning,
um, I remember hearing a number of
different philosophers who were working
on on AI talking about, okay, well, we
have, you know, we have carbon based
brain, so we're, you know, we're, you
know, is, I guess it's like three pounds
of matter. Um, we have neural networks,
and that limits our ability to to reason
at a certain speed. But, um, with
silicon, you know, and and the, um, the
chips that AI is running, the the speed
is essentially light speed. It's there
there's no there's no telling how
quickly the reasoning the developments
the advancements um how does that work
in terms of training AI we you know I
know that you know initially I I think
it was in the 1950s or 1960s when they
you know there was those students at
Dartmouth who said we're going to spend
a summer and see if we can resolve we
can resolve a machine audiovisisual um
you know progress and obviously you know
the last you know I guess 70 years or so
we've seen enormous progress where how
quickly do you foresee the advancements
uh in AI by arriving at okay more
creative fields or more you know
embodied robotics that are going to
start to you know enter into different
fields that might not be seen right now
>> well I mean it's uh progress has been
exceptional I think I don't think any of
us could have predicted how quickly we'd
be progressing
>> um so I don't think it'll be long before
we start seeing um AI you know ex
certainly exceed the computational
capabilities of of of the human brain
>> right I mean right now AI's in some ways
they do already I mean certainly I mean,
their ability to memorize vast swaths of
information and retrieve said
information and spit out answers is
certainly I think well beyond what the
human brain is capable of.
>> Um, but that being said that they're
still not capable of the same kind of
critical thinking that we are and there
certainly that their their intelligence
is is still fairly narrow. So, one way
to think about this is is as I mentioned
before in the STEM fields because though
there's a lot of commonalities between
those fields, right? A lot of underlying
principles which are fairly consistent.
they um they tend to be very good and
and in fact they're benchmarking now at
at PhD level and beyond.
>> That's extraordinary.
>> Yeah. I mean I mean the more most recent
model most intelligent model in the
world right now is said to be kind of
Grock 4 and and that that uh that model
has uh exceptional uh capabilities. Um I
mean and that certainly would have PhD
capability in most in most domains. But
that being said just because it has PhD
capability doesn't necessarily mean it's
capable of the same kind of innovation
that the human brain is. Right? So when
we say PhD building, what it basically
means is that um you know the average
you know state-of-the-art model um can
can you know basically answer the same
kind of questions that a PhD student can
answer, right? And but that really just
what that really means is that they're
able to retain critical information and
apply it in innumerable cases kind of
like a PhD could. But that doesn't mean
that they're they're capable of the same
kind of uh innovation or invention,
right? That's a different kind of thing
because you know they're trained on
large swaths of data and they're able to
then uh identify patterns in those datas
and they're able to then use those
patterns to to make certain kinds of
inferences but like invention and
innovation is something something unique
right we have a truly original idea and
and I and I I don't think we're there
and I think mo most of the heads of the
AI labs would acknowledge we haven't we
haven't got there yet like these these
models are not capable of true invention
so I think we still have that edge and
part of that I think is
>> invention um you know goes beyond just
memor memorizing information and pattern
recognition, right? It requires uh like
a spark of of uh creative, you know, uh
you know, innovation, ingenuity. There's
something something unique about that
whole process.
>> Um but I think that that's something
probably in the next year or two we
might we might see AI capable of capable
of doing that.
>> And Matthew, in terms of um you know,
AI's participating in the creative act
in that sense. Um creativity obviously
is something that there are individuals
of genius who have foresight who are
able to to see things make connections
that we we might not think or not be
able to see yet. But um obviously
sometimes that also requires a community
that requires you know human dialogue
and that ability of of people to
communicate at large levels and come up
and work together on um on a common
goal. A lot of the great inventions of
of society have been done that way. Do
you see AIs um you know working together
or are AI systems able to communicate
with one another um to to work on
something and in a weird way you get a
cluster of super AIs you know solving
problems or are the current AI models
you know all individual based on one
program one problem and
>> no no they they work they're working
together more and more and I think
that's that's obviously going to be uh
enormously beneficial for us I mean
these machines having um you know
memorized and and and uh crunched some
of the, you know, the best data from the
brightest minds.
>> They're they're a they're great aids in
invention, right, in the process. And so
more and more what we're starting to
see, like there are limits to the the
current uh modalities, you know, for
training right now. I mean, there's only
so much you can do in pre-training,
post- training, right? And and now we
have this new reinforcement learning
>> paradigm, which is um which is
enormously helpful, right? I mean where
you you basically give them you set uh
an environment
>> for them to learn and then they
basically kind of unleash them in the
environment in the same way kind of a
baby learns when you unleash it in the
house and let it crawl around right um
these these AIs kind of learn through
interacting with the environment
>> and and that's that's that's incredible
because that means that we don't have to
like feed them a whole bunch of you know
pairs which in which case we become the
bottleneck as I said before they're able
to kind of learn just by interacting
right
>> and so so this has allowed them to kind
of take off and we've seen this in like
models like deepseeek and stuff um they
were one of the first to come out there
and really demonst demonstrate the the
power of of reinforcement reinforcement
learning
>> and and now and now yes these models are
starting to work together in tandem now
they have been for for I would say like
a year or two
>> you know we've had situations where we
have you give a submit a prompt and you
may have multiple models um generate
answers and then you may have one kind
of teacher model which will evaluate the
answers and pick the best one right so
we have had this kind of orchestration
happening in the past but but now we're
starting to see that uh they're
leveraging uh new techniques like tree
search moni search and which is you know
basically and this has
If you remember that with Go when when
when AI beat the best Go player in the
world, right? Um you know that was that
was remarkable and that was that move 37
if you recall was was one of the few
examples of a truly original uh move
that we have from an AI system, right?
It it posited a move that the human
experts just couldn't understand why it
did this. Um and so that that was really
cool. Um and and one of the one of the
ways that that AI was able to to beat
the best go player in the world was was
leveraging this this technique called
tree search where it plays itself
millions of times and and and what it
does is is it um it looks it knows the
board. So it knows it knows the it knows
the environment and knows the rules and
it can like suggest moves to itself,
right? Innumerable kind of moves and
strategies and then it kind of evaluates
how they may play out and therefore it
picks, you know, one of those particular
strategies. the next move and and and uh
and and so because it has this ability
to kind of
>> um to propose all these different
possibilities and then and then to kind
of test them all and then obviously one
of those moves will will ultimately
contribute to a victory or contribute to
a loss and then it can feed that that
information back and say hm how did that
particular move you know help me or hurt
me and it can learn from that this this
this tree search is is really is really
going to be critically important and so
right now that's not AI haven't been
able to leverage that but there are by
merging these these kind of tree search
techniques which allowed you know um
AlphaGo to beat the best Go player in
the world. If we can combine that with
generative AI models, I think that's
going to be a massive unlock and and and
so part of this is if you have multiple
models, you know, you have multiple GR
force which are all all this tree
search, you know, capability combined
and they're all doing search across. I
mean, you put this all together and it
becomes, you know, what they'll be able
to do to advance science, I think will
be quite enormous. And I think that they
will actually be able to explore um uh
you know, areas of science and and
propose hypothesis that we haven't even
conceived of. and they may come back
with really interesting results. Deise
Asabis like talks about kind of three
different three three different ways of
understanding like intelligence like you
know you have interpolation
>> which would be an example like in the
case of AI uh like a diffusion model is
a good example where you train a model
on images of cats right and then then
you ask the model to generate um a new
image of of a cat that that doesn't
exist right and so what it does it kind
of calculates it kind of takes all that
statistical data all the images of the
cats and it produces one that is unique
So it's it's unique in the sense that
that cat as it as you know as you see it
does not appear in its train data but
it's but you know but it was it was it
arrived at that cat via statistical like
you know
>> um and another one would be
extrapolation
>> and this would be um how the AI and the
alpha go arrived at that move 37 right
>> where it uh it proposes you know uh
different moves to itself and and it it
it finds one particular that it thinks
you know is worth is worth applying and
uh and and it turns out that that's
True. And so that would be the example
of like you know extrapolation move 37
but uh in invention right in innovation
is something something different and so
you know these models even working
together in tandem we haven't seen any
relevance that are capable of truly
original thought. Um at least I'm not
aware of any that I think are really
convincing but I think that's something
that might be possible in in a in a year
or so.
>> Wow. That's thrilling, but it's also,
you know, um dissling in in certain
sense to think of um these alien
intelligences, you know, starting to
create and act. And um Matthew when you
look ahead let's say in the next you
know the next year but then also a
little bit further along maybe the next
5 10 years um and we see these these AIs
that have um enormous capabilities that
have access to all of the data that
humans have ever created and they're
able to innovate think reason at a speed
that we can't even um imagine. you know,
some people start to get very nervous
about that and and that's I think that's
been, you know, categorized and and and
shown in uh in popular culture and films
and it's it's hard almost to to see a
popular film where there's a really
great wonderful robot that that solves
all our problems. It's often much more
dystopian. um when we look at at culture
and then we look at these AIs who then
will start to create and and and and
impose themselves in certain ways uh
much more on our life um a lot of people
are really nervous. What what do you
where do you see where do you see this
going and how do you see you know
society adapting and there was a recent
article that came out from Goldman Sachs
um the the you know the great uh uh bank
and they said that in the next 10 years
they anticipate more than 25% of jobs
going away and I know there's there's
you know there's much more
>> I I think that's I think that's uh
that's way too conservative. I don't
think that's true. I think it's much
higher. I I think if
if you think of of the way the economic
system works, right, I'm sorry to
interrupt you, but no, but I just, you
know, I I I find that those those are
not those kind of like more conservative
claims are not entirely helpful. Um
>> because I think
>> our problem right now is is that AI is
significantly underhyped in the long
term. Sometimes it's overhyped in the in
the in the short short term,
>> but it's certainly underhyped in the
long term. And I think saying things
like, you know, AI and robots in the
next 10 years are going to are going to,
you know, wipe out 20% of jobs is is
absurd. Um,
>> because
>> you think it's cuz they're nervous
because they don't want people
>> I think so. I think so. I, you know, I
think that they're, you know, they want
to rattle people, you know, and I'm not
trying to say that they're dishonest.
And I'm I'm sure that the data they
have, you know, that number they arrived
at via, you know, u, they had a
particular approach and that and they
they they believe confidently that's the
right
>> that's the right number. I just think
that that's that's incorrect and it just
kind of ignores certain kind of um
realities. I mean um about how the
economic system works. I mean if you
think about like let's just take AI and
robots, right? So you you have your your
disembodied AIs that live that live in
>> live live in large uh you know inference
compute clusters
>> um that you know and those jobs right
now we already we already can see those
jobs are starting to to uh replace uh
coders. Absolutely. And and now now
they're starting to come after white
collar works workers, right?
>> Yeah. So
>> data analytics,
>> data analytics, I mean I think the law,
the medicine fields, I think all these
fields. Um and and you think about with
these more recent models are coming out,
they're they're capability in regards to
like diagnostics for for medicine,
right? Or their ability to predict
market trends and things. I mean,
they're they're next they're next level.
I mean, they're truly truly ne next
level. So if I'm a company and and I'm a
for-profit company and so what our
shareholders want is us to make money,
right? And I have this this AI this this
kind of super AI which is capable of of
you know predicting market trends better
than you know any 10 20 you know 30
people combined. Well and and I and I'm
in this competitive landscape where I I
have I have to you know be ahead of the
curve. um the idea that I'm going to
choose not to use AI because I have 30
employees who are not as capable but but
I have some loyalty to them and so I'm
going to keep them in I mean I think
that's just that's not realistic and I I
so I think that they they will feel
immense pressure to let those 30 people
go and choose the AI because that will
allow them to stay to stay competitive
and and I can you can see that that
playing out that tension in almost any
any field especially office work right
and then you start thinking about robots
which are you know basically embodied
AIs and you start thinking about blue
collar work. So, you know, anything that
um is is a highly repetitive task um
that doesn't require a lot of
generalized learning. So, so let's say
like a factory like a factory
environment like uh robots can you know
can work let's say 18 hours a day they
stop to charge and that's basically and
now what we're finding is able their
ability to swap their own batteries out
which you know takes about 90 seconds to
do and then they're back on the back on
the line right so you think about this
robot you you pay once and you maybe
have some you know some very low
maintenance costs but for the most part
they're on the line and they could work
for five five to 10 years right in
principle and then you think of a human
employee and what you have to pay them
every year you have to pay them, right?
And there's benefits and other things.
Just think about that again from a from
a competitive uh point of view. I these
these these factories will not be able
to compete unless they they move
towards, you know, greater and greater
automation. So, and you think about you
start looking at all all the jobs that
are currently out there. And if we think
about the robots and the AIS, how many
are likely to feel this competitive
pressure? Almost all of them.
>> Almost all of them. So, to say 25% is
absurd. The only thing I think that's
that that's slowing down this transition
is because AI capabilities they're still
not they're still very narrow in their
intelligence. They're not generalized,
right? So they difficulty moving from
STEM as we talked about to other fields.
But as we get closer and closer to
artificial general intelligence and they
become their their intelligence becomes
more and more general, meaning they're
having PhD capability in even more
domains, you're going to start to see
them move more and more to white collar
work. And as the AI start to get um as
we I mean there's a big manufacturing
challenge right now with robots, right?
as as the AI as more and more AI get
released into the world and they start
learning from interacting with the
environment again like children they're
going to get better at navigating this
environment we're already seeing like
Teslas and autopilot very capable of
amazing things and so really we just
have this manufacturing bottleneck the
AI will be there in the next year or two
they'll be fairly generalized I think to
be able to work in most environments
you're going to see those robots just
just flood the market so I mean I think
realistically in the horizon of 10 years
um you could look at 80 90% of GDP
economy jobs just being gone that's not
to say there won't be other jobs that
created uh possibly but I I I do think
it's it's going to mean that we have to
start thinking beyond like you know just
you know defining my value based upon
how much I contribute to the GDP economy
right and that that has to be more to
life than that because I just don't
think there's going to be opportunities
a lot of opportunities in those areas
except for those who are like people
that are uniquely capable of hybridizing
with AI systems right it's not said
there won't be humans involved um there
will be but these people are going to be
you know the elite who are uniquely
capable of working with machines you
know Um, and and and that's going to be
a very small percentage of the
population.
>> And Matthew, hearing this, I um first
off, I don't I mean, I know maybe now
people are starting to talk about this,
but I don't hear in in the general
conversation online about AI um you
know, people looking at that future and
being able to um to paint something
that's really positive because I think a
lot of people if they hear 90% next 10
years uh and I'm not, you know, I'm not
going to be able to uh contribute or
compete. Um I I obviously I can see a
lot of people going into a very dark
place. I can also see, you know,
political sentiment, social sentiment
that goes against AI, that goes against
um this uh this innovation or this
continued development. Where where do
you see things going um in terms of the
the social response to this, the
political response, and then of course
we're going to get to the church,
>> right? Well, I mean I I think a a lot of
it comes down to how honest we are with
pe with people and and how and how
serious like we we we we you know we
take we we we acknowledge this
challenge. I mean so let me start start
with like the being honest with the
people.
So some of the heads of the AI labs I
think are trying to be be more to be
honest with people about the possibility
for the technology which is super
exciting but also also the challenges
>> and and I think it's very clear this
this could kind of break in in two
different ways. That's that's how I see
it anyway. One is
we are honest with people. we about
where the techn is headed and and that
that's that stokes a very robust and
honest uh civil conversation and you
know and and and that civil conversation
then informs the policies of our our you
know our elected representatives and and
they enact um you laws regulations to
ensure that this this technological
transition happens uh in a way that's
likely not to impede human flourishing
right to not necessarily um slow down
the technological ical development but
ensures that people's basic necessities
are met and that people are comfortable
that they'll have a meaning and purpose
right in the future. So, so I think a
lot of this is just making sure that
that the right information makes it to
the people so they can they can discuss
how what kind of future they want to
build together and ensure that their
politicians are passing the right laws
to help us arrive at that better future.
And again, a lot of this is contingent
upon how clearly I I think, you know,
our leaders can can sell a vision of the
future in which we're kind of working
alongside Aon robots. I mean, I think
that that's a really critical critical
part of this. I mean, as Cardinal
Collins used to always say, I mean, if
you know where you're going, you're more
likely to get there. So, I think we do
need to collectively have a sense for
how our world could be better, like what
the right relationship of AI and robots
is, in what areas should they be
involved in, what are shouldn't they be,
and how how could human beings be living
in in like, you know, in 20 years, how
do we want to live? How do we want our
kids to grow up? And I think if we can
get clear about what kind of world we
want to build, then we can work
backwards, you know, and and and we can
make sure we're passing the right laws
uh in order to arrive at arrive there.
>> And Matthew, it seems at the moment that
the political leadership, at least in
the United States, is is very concerned
and very focused on well, we are in a
geopolitical and technological race with
China. And it seems that the um the
attention is on we need to arrive at AGI
as fast as possible because of course
this would allow whoever arrives there
first will have enormous leverage on on
the rest of the world economy and I
think that that speed and that that I
guess anxiety around getting there first
or or the the fear that's the other side
you know China will arrive there first
is making it so that there doesn't seem
to be um as much foresight on okay what
happens when we arrive there or how do
we have this civil conversation because
the general public at least online when
I'm paying attention, they don't feel
that, you know, they they didn't vote
for, okay, my data is going to be used
to train, you know, this AI or um, you
know, I I'm I have all these concerns
about AI in general, and no one is is um
is voting on this or or or even even
able to to cautiously put the the the
brakes on certain things out of security
measures,
>> right? I mean, so I mean, the first
thing I I mean, I I probably just start
by saying the race with China is real
and I think it's very serious. I think,
you know, I think all all of us who grow
up in the west, you know, appreciate um
our western values and our western way
of life and and China in many ways has a
different understanding of the way the
world should should kind of work and and
so uh whatever whatever country uh
achieves artificial general intelligence
first will be at an enormous advantage
economically, militarily and of course
that you know with AGI um once they have
a AGI they can then replicate those
AGIs, right? and those artificial
general intelligence. I mean that that
will be an enormous enormous boon to
them and and that will allow them as a
country to get ahead but also I think
will increase their sphere of influence
right because they'll be able to
generate a lot of prosperity at home and
then in principle be able to share that
prosperity with with allies
>> and so I I I do I do understand the
pressure I mean I I I do think I do want
the US because principally they're the
leader in AI right now. I do want them
to win win this race,
but um yeah, it's not something that,
you know, um I don't think this the
average person, the average citizen has
been really informed about what's going
on here, what the stakes are and feel
like like they have real agency in this.
The decision to engage, you know, China
in this this kind of new, you know, uh
cold war um has certainly been certainly
been been made by our leaders. I don't
think I don't think it's I don't think
it's um I think it makes sense. That's
why they're elected, right? to make
these kind of calls and the technology
moving so quickly. You know, it'd be
difficult to have a referendum on it,
right? I mean, that would take time. Um,
>> but I do think it does pose real risks.
Um, and and I don't think it's not
certainly we cannot take for granted the
West is going to win. I mean, I mean,
there's a good chance that China will
win this at least initially. Now,
hopefully we won't be too far behind and
we can kind of, you know, check each
other, but I think there's a there's a
real chance that China China could get
get ahead and there's all for all all
kinds of reasons. Um, and so I I think I
think this is going to play out and I
don't think there's much we can do about
it, right? I think, you know, China and
the US are going to compete to to get to
>> AGI.
>> So, you know, trying to slow down the
technology, I uh I just don't think that
that's realistic. And so, I think I
think our time and energy is better is
better spent uh uh focused on ensuring
that we don't leave people behind.
Um and I and I think if the church
focuses more of its time and energy on
that and and about um helping humanity
to reminding humanity about what life's,
you know, supposed to be about and what
civilization is supposed to be about and
and making it clear what kind of future
better future we should be paddling
towards. I think will uh that that's a
much better project that than than just,
you know, uh lobbying to try to slow the
slow the technology down to allow time
for people to adapt. I just don't think
it's realistic. And then Matthew, before
we we get to the the church's role with
um with, you know, helping steward and
and guide the ship as we approach AGI,
could you please unpack what AGI,
artificial general intelligence is, what
um what it in theory um will look like,
and then of course it's just a stones
throw away from ASI, artificial super
intelligence.
>> Sure. Yeah. I guess we've been dropping
that term quite a few times. E so I mean
artificial general intelligence. Well,
let me put it this way that today what
we're interacting with for the most part
is artificial narrow intelligence,
right? Um, so basically it means that
you you an AI system has been trained on
on a specific domain and is and is
excellent within that respective domain.
So it has has a high level of of
intelligence in a specific domain. But
if you were to then move that particular
AI to another domain, right, its
intelligence is very brittle. It would
it would start to fall apart. it's not
able to kind of generalize what it's
learned in in this one domain and and
apply it that well in another. Now um
this is certainly the case on on um more
classical AI systems. I mean they were
very very narrow. I mean now with now
with uh generative AI we're finding that
actually the AI are getting better and
better at um you know generalizing what
they know on let's say STEM and applying
it to even something like we talked
about earlier philosophy or theology.
But that being said, uh right now what
what we're really seeing is AIS excel
within within STEM and coding, right?
And and they're not as good in in in the
humanities. An artificial general
general intelligence as as the name
implies wouldn't have that that that
constraint.
So in principle um it it would be
capable of of computing essentially
anything that's that's computable. And
and so you think think of it like this.
I mean you know one of the the founder
of like classical of of of classical
computing I mean is is Alan Turring and
and and he had this thing called his
understanding of something called the
Turing machine right and in principle
for him a human brain is kind of like a
turning machine right it's the human
brain is uniquely capable of really uh
crunching and processing um and
analyzing really anything that can be
crunched and analyzed and processed and
and so uh I think you know Turing would
probably say that an artificial general
intelligence should be in principle
capable of what that which the human
brain can do
>> and and So like now there's different
ways of of like defining AGI but that's
the way that I understand it and that's
the way like someone like Denise Has
from Deep Mind and others would define
it. So an artificial general
intelligence to me would be an AI which
is capable of of let's just say PhD
level capability in multiple domains and
and beyond a particular like like STEM.
I think if if we saw an AI demonstrate
that level of um capability, I I think
we we would have effectively hit a AGI
>> and an AGI would for all intents and
purposes supersede the the an average
person in in almost any field. I mean it
would
>> yeah I I mean I guess you know some
people some people argue that I mean I I
think
my as far as I'm concerned if if an AI
was was able to to demonstrate I there's
a number of different ways of of of uh
testing for like general intelligence
there's one called the arc challenge
right and like you know generalized
intelligence or fluid intelligence is
actually is a very specific you know
it's very specific and it's very very
hard and and you know and and like Yan
Lun is who's the head of Meta AI's uh
division u talks a lot about this. I
mean, you know, the amount of data that
that babies crunch, right? Um, in order
to build that world model which allows
them to effectively operate in the world
is immense. I mean, we we we I mean the
models that we train today, the the
large language models are trained on
basically all all the text data we have
on the internet, which is like 20 20
trillion tokens now. It's it's always
growing, but um and and that that allows
them to be, you know, pretty pretty uh
masterfully um understand language,
right? and and they they've been able to
you know leverage that understanding and
then you know when they have access to
other forms of data like in chemistry
biology and chemistry and math and stuff
they're able to but for the most part um
despite all of that data which seems
like a lot they still suck at like
general intelligence tasks right I mean
um which is which is kind of surprising
right until you until you understand how
much data a baby's brain is processing
right in it its first few years right I
mean like so for instance
um I I 20 20 trillion tokens, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So that data like if you were to add up
all that data, a baby has crunched more
data than that simply through through
vision. So that one sensory modality by
the time they're four years old for four
years old.
>> Wow.
>> And that's just one sensor sensory
modality, right? So you think about like
in order for a baby to operate in the
world, right, at baby levels,
>> it has to crunch um mass amounts of data
in multiple modalities to build an
effective world model. So we shouldn't
be surprised when an AI when we give it
all access to you know language which is
discreet right because language only
expresses understanding at a very kind
of high level of abstraction. So we
shouldn't be surprised when we put an AI
in a robot, it's banging around in
things, right? I mean, of course, right?
And and so building effective world
models is is absolutely, you know, key
um to to general intelligence as far as
I'm concerned. You know, we talked about
the the age of experience for AIs and
this is where I talked about it earlier
where you really what you want to do is
in some ways allow the AI to embody the
AI, allow it to interact with the
environment and learn like a child does,
right? So you give it the sensor
modality, similar sensor modalities, you
just let it interact and learn from
first principles, right? that that's a
better way to train a model because it's
less dependent on human data which is
not always high quality, right? Or or
may not actually reflect the ground
truth.
>> Mhm.
>> So, so AGI uh is going to require a a
number of tactical breakthroughs to get
there. I think a lot of the labs feel
they know what those those are. I guess
I guess we'll see if they're right. And
I think maybe somewhere between at two
to five years, we'll probably we'll
probably achieve um artificial general
intelligence. And then once we've
achieved artificial general
intelligence, we can then work with that
artificial general intelligence to help
us achieve artificial super
intelligence. Again, artificial and
super intelligence is kind of a it's
difficult to define depends who you
depends who you ask. I I I tend to think
of artificial artificial super
intelligence is is an is an artificial
intelligence which in principle is
computational capability exceeds that of
the entire human race.
>> Wow.
>> So, and you can imagine uh the effect
that would have on the world if that
were to exist. So, and again that's I
don't think we effectively know how to
build that
>> yet, but AG working working with AGI, we
probably we probably could figure it out
and and the the you know, the thought is
that if we have AGIS, we could we could
build a you know a whole fleet of those
things. And and that would allow us to
to make rapid progress towards
artificial super intelligence. And so
you can see why like getting to AGI for
China and for the US is such a big deal,
right? Because it's thought that whoever
gets AGI first, they they may it may not
be able to possibly catch them, right?
they just may run away and and um all
the way up to artificial super
intelligence.
>> Yeah. And the and the acceleration that
would happen with with AGIS working
together, I I find that that there would
be a telescoping in terms of time that
certain progress that seemed impossible
would within months or or years would
would arrive. And so then, Matthew,
looking at all that and the enormous
transformations that are are, you know,
on our horizon, um, where what role does
the church have in in in in being in
dialogue with this and in stewarding the
faithful who I'm sure I I I know
actually that that have all sorts of
questions, anxieties, and concerns. And
already we're coming from a society that
that already has a lot of things to work
on to to improve. Um, there is, you
know, economic distress, there's there's
social tensions for all all different
reasons. Um I feel like you know you put
AI in there and you you remove um jobs
which give a lot of people purpose. Um
you
>> yes but I think it's important to
acknowledge what is one of the primary
motivators like why are some of the
smartest people in the world working so
hard on AI right and not like you know
curing cancer right or or giving us the
flying cars that we're all supposed to
have right that uh the digestion
promised me right that never
materialized
um because they think that AI will help
us crack these problems and I think
they're right I totally think they're
right I mean look look at me hassabis
and deep minds and protein folding in,
right? Extraordinary. I mean, it's
extraordinary. So, without a doubt, you
know, as AIs get smarter, they're going
to be able to help us crack a lot of
these problems. And so, things like
disease and stuff, we we may actually be
able to crack that. I mean, I mean, that
does feel it does feel like that that is
inevitable at at this point if the
technology continues continues to to
progress. I I I think poverty is is
another one, right? I mean, how do we
solve poverty?
>> I think a lot of people feel that AI
will help us get there. AI and robots. I
mean, they're going to be able to
produce goods and services. I mean, I
mean, for for prices like we never we
never like conceived of before. So,
there is there is a real likelihood that
it'll create a rising tide and it'll
lift potentially billions out of
poverty. So, that's exciting, right? And
and that's I mean you think about if we
were to if we just address everybody's
Maslo needs like you know ensuring they
have shelter you know they have food you
know that their kids are are going to be
you know well educated and they'll have
opportunities ahead of them.
>> If you take away those pressures from
people I think that that that could even
help us address things like war and
conflict. You know, I think I think I
mean I'm no expert in in these things,
but but but generally I would say a lot
of conflicts are driven by scarcity and
the ability, you know, as people
manipulate others and tell them if we
don't do this your your kids are going
to starve and
>> we have to do this and so I think if but
but if AI and robots allows everyone to
have a fairly decent standard of living
and we take away those masalates, I
think it becomes harder to justify, you
know, violence, right? Um, so, so I do
think that the the hyper on this
technology in that way is very real and
and and I'm very optimistic. That being
said, there is this, you know, as we
talked about before, the existential
cliff that I do worry about a lot,
right? I mean, and and again, you know,
we've seen it in movies and television,
right? I mean, let's say you make kind
of a better world in the sense that
people aren't, you know, dying of
disease anymore and everyone's got a
home and and their kids are able to
learn and so that all sounds great, but
there there is this whole issue of
purpose, right, in meaning. And so then
what do I do with with this time that I
that I now been been gifted, right? And
and that that's I think remains a big
problem as it as it always been. you
know without the proper you know human
intellectual and spiritual formation as
we say in the church I don't know if
we'll we'll know how to constructively
use that time and we could end up you
know chasing dopamine hits right right
off of a cliff and that is something
that that really concerns me and this is
why I feel so strongly that the we must
succeed at the new evangelization I
think all of us have to really now focus
as much in time and energy as we can in
ensuring that we're we're preaching the
gospel you know and we're taking
advantage of every opportunity we and to
to to share the gospel with others,
which is why I'm so passionate about um
Catholic AI.
>> Yeah. And so, Matthew, um you said the
magic word there, Catholic AI. What what
what is Catholic AI? Where where can the
church insert itself into this
conversation and into these, you know,
these these new machines, these new ways
of of communicating and and discovering
information?
>> Well, I mean, Catholic AI I mean, I
don't I don't know if there's an
official definition. I mean, you know, I
think we're we're kind of pioneering in
this space. we're kind of figuring as we
go along. But the way I understand
Catholic AI is is is essentially the the
it's the desire to create artificial
intelligence is um that are aligned um
with let's say the magisterium of the
Catholic Church. So in a technical terms
we could say that the objective function
of Catholic AI
>> is fidelity. So that that's a Catholic
AI system. So a an AI system which tries
as faithfully as possible to to
reproduce and be faithful to that which
the church teaches. That's it. That's
that's Catholic AI. And so and that's
different from from like secular AI,
right? Like from what you know Gemini
and and Claude and and Chhat GPT are
because their objective function is not
fidelity. I mean their objective
functions I don't know you know what
their objective functions are. I mean
obviously increased capabilities is
their objective function. Get to AGI
seems to be the you know the kind of the
objective function. Um but it's not it's
not fidelity. So it's not to say that
they can't effectively reproduce or pair
it with the church teaches, right? But
but um um suffice it to say not as well
as as an AI which is totally built to
ensure that it's faithful, right? So
that's why I think there's a place for
Catholic AI be I think it's needed. It's
absolutely needed. Um you know it it's
it's the reason why we even got into
this in the first place is because we
knew people were using chatbt. They're
asking philosophical, theological, moral
questions. And and like I said, uh
Chachi may knock it out of the park
eight, nine times out of 10. But how
comfortable are we with that one or two
times out of 10? It totally hallucinates
something and leads someone astray. I'm
not not cool with that, right? And and
so the question is, can we can we get
can we get it, you know, to have a
better batting average than that? And
and I think we've we've demonstrated
that yes, yes, we can, but it takes a
lot of focused attention
>> and and so so that that's kind of the
Catholic AI AI project. And Matthew, how
do you ensure fidelity?
>> Well, it's not easy. Um,
and when we started Madison
basically as a research project, that
was kind of, you know, that was kind of
the question, you know, h how can can we
take state-of-the-art models or soda
models as we call them and can we teach
them to be faithful? And long story
short, uh yeah, you c you can you can,
but it's it's not perfect. And that part
of that is because it's just the nature
of generative AI. It's
non-deterministic, right? I mean, for
those of you who don't know what like
non-determinism, generative AI models,
basically what it means is um uh when
you when you prompt an AI, we we we
can't be certain what it's going to say.
um we can we can try and and ensure that
the outcome is as desirable as possible
or as aligned as possible but it's never
it's never 100% certain
when you and and that of course
determine determinism would be the
opposite of that right where and and and
more classical AI systems are kind of
capable of this right where you you give
it a prompt and you can you're actually
can make sure that the answer is exactly
what you predicted
>> so so in that sense like leveraging
generative a models is a challenge right
because We're not looking for kind of
creativity um in in doctrine and dogma.
We don't we don't want it to interpret
it in unique and novel ways. We want it
to be faithful. We want but uh but we
found through a number of techniques
that you can significantly reduce the
probability of of hallucination. And so
there's you know there's a number of
different ways we we've effectively been
able to do this. One is ensuring that
everything that the AI says is grounded
in a source. And so this is something we
call retriever augmented generation.
Mhm.
>> And and so so in in essence what you do
and what we've had to do is is basically
get everything the church has ever said
and that's been digitized and put it
together in a knowledge base. Right now
I think our knowledge base is just over
u 27,000 Catholic theological and
philosophical texts and that includes
all the compendiums and you know you
know uh all the council documents I
think you know documents like the
eriticon and other important sources the
the teachings of the doctrines of the
church
>> and and and so that that's a fairly
broad distribution of of you know u not
broad enough but but it's certainly and
then essentially when someone asks a
question
>> uh kind of one AI system goes and and
checks to see what documents are
relevant to answering that question. So
we call that a retriever and it goes and
retrieves all the all the relevant
chunks parts of the document which are
relevant to answering that question. It
retrieves them and then basically it pro
it passes those on to to an AI which is
then responsible for like distilling
them. So and and and providing providing
an answer but everything it says has to
be grounded in one of those documents
and the idea is to have as much
transparency there as possible. So when
the AI does generate its answer it
provides inline citations so the user
can check and see why did you say that?
they can they can go and check the
original source to make sure it's true.
This is not something effectively that
that secularized systems do. You know,
uh you know, they're starting to
introduce uh you know, research mode,
right? Where they go and check websites
and or reverse rag where they'll
generate an answer and they'll find s
documents to validate what they're
saying. But again, there's always a
question of what sources are you using?
How do I know those are the right
sources? And this this can be like
tedious because you have to then check
and make sure that the sources it
checked on the web, how faithful are how
much do I trust those? Whereas our
knowledge base is really just official
church teaching and and you know what
would be considered to be the most
authoritative um Catholic theological
philosophical text and so in that sense
you don't have to check the sources. So,
so rag is is is one approach retrie
retrieve augmented generation.
>> And Matthew, how do you how do you
select the sources? I imagine, you know,
with with the Catholic data set where
with with um Catholic uh knowledge and
that's been created over 2,000 years.
There's just there's I imagine there's
Catholic theologians have talked about
almost every subject. How do how do you
and and the team select and then also
prioritize in terms of hierarchy of oh
this is from a pope or this is from a
church father? Well, they definitely
haven't talked about every subject
because because we become painfully
aware of aware of that. They certainly
have covered a lot of um you know moral
ground, philosophical, theological uh
ground. Um the big challenge of course
is is kind of the every everyday
day-to-day people's experiences, right?
I mean, when they go and start asking
questions about that, it's difficult
because obviously they they weren't
writing for a particular person's
experience necessarily. So, so that's a
challenge, but that's that's a rabbit
hole we can get into if you want. But
how do we go about selecting sources?
Well, I mean it's actually not that it's
not really rocket science. So, I mean we
do have a scholarly advisory board which
>> uh is is chaired by some, you know, some
some notable heads of political
universities and things like that. And
so, you know, we went to we started
having this conversation about where
should we start and they said we start
with fundamental magisterial teaching,
right? So, start with the the the
fundamental doc dogmas and doctrines of
the church. So, um the catechisms, the
you know, the council documents and
things and and essentially, you know,
once we once we had that we're still
we're still getting that together and we
have all the contemporary stuff. If
we're still going back and trying to get
our hands on all the ancient stuff, then
it's just a question of then um going
from the extraordinary magisterium, how
much of the ordinary magisterium do we
embrace, right? So that would be like,
you know, the reflections of the bishops
and the popes and things. Um and so, you
know, the simple answer is we try and
start with the most we try and grab the
most authoritative stuff, right? So
that's where we started.
>> Mh.
>> And then slowly but surely we've been
expanding that out to include the
doctrines of the church, the church
fathers and and then you know um even
some some bishop's conferences metastial
teaching homalies of the pope's general
audiences. We've been focusing a lot on
that lately, namely because those
general audiences and homalies um are
incredible examples of uh you know
basically human beings ability to
distill from, you know, from like like
very complicated theological texts and
these this pope in 15 minutes distills
it down for people to understand, right?
While at the same time reflecting on why
it's relevant to the world like these
kind of examples of distillation for AI
are really important
>> because people come and and they'll
bring like a very generalized situation.
Here's what's going on in my life. What
would the church say to me?
>> And this was a big problem when we
started. It freaked us out. I mean, I at
one point I was wondering if we we we
should even be doing this. And and then
the only reason we continued namely uh
because I didn't think with especially
with the early eyes which weren't that
intelligent. I I wasn't sure if we
should was I realized if we stop um
people are just going to take those
questions at chatbt and I mean at least
for us we're trying our objective
function is fidelity, right? So I
thought, well, we got to we got to stay
at we got to stay at this, right?
Because it's better it's better than
than just going back to secular um AIS.
But this this issue of someone sharing a
particular situation, being able to sure
that the AI is then able to understand
from first principles what the church
teaches and then apply it to that
particular situation. The the best way
like we found to enable or I should say
the way that we found that was most
effective to allow the AI to do that was
just by showing innumerable examples of
the popes and and other uh notable
people in the church doing it. And then
the AI was just a was able to kind of
figure it out.
>> And then Matthew, the the fact that that
you and and the team have have ingested
have um have digitized all this
incredible body of work. This is
something that that's unique that only
Magisterium or Mayi has because I I
think of you know users who who may be
watching who have questions and they
might go to a chat GBT or a Gemini and
and um and you know maybe maybe in some
cases they provide the right answer but
often a lot of times and this happened
to me specifically we get hallucinations
where all of a sudden the AI is
generating an answer that is not
grounded in in in a text or in in
tradition or in anything based on
fidelity. Could you um could you speak
on hallucinations and and and what that
is and and and why that that takes
place?
>> Well, first let me just say just to
define what it is. So hallucination
essentially is when an AI uh makes
something up and it's coming I think
it's sort of coming from a good place. I
mean it's very eager to please. It wants
to give you an answer, right? And
sometimes um it maybe wasn't trained on
on on the data it needs to answer and so
it just kind of
>> it just kind of makes it up, right? So
it's not grounded in in any in anything.
Um and so this is particularly problem
when you're we're dealing in the realm
of facts where when it hallucinates a
fact. So it passes something off as a
fact but in fact it's not actually a
fact. This it's not true. So this is
this is a hallucination and and
obviously they've been a problem in
generative AI from the very beginning.
Now AI systems as they they got better
uh the the the likelihood of
hallucinations is going down over time.
And if you combine it with other
techniques like rag and and prompt
engineering and and uh and tooling, you
can you can bring that probability down.
And that's what we've been able to
effectively demonstrate with with
metasti
but um but but hallucinations I think at
least for the foreseeable future will
remain a problem as long as you know
you're using generative generative AI.
It's just just it's just one of the
again like the way gener models it's
just it's it's calculating probabilities
and it's doing next token prediction
right and sometimes those those
statistical predictions are wrong. So,
and if you compound compound like next
token prediction one token after another
uh it tends to be like we call it like
exponential drift like the longer it
talks the probability that it'll just
kind of go off it it'll these these
statistical errors can compound and it
can just go off in some weird tangent
which is why this is a very difficult
you know problem to solve but we're get
I think we're getting closer um to
cracking it
>> and Matthew when you look at the uh the
major LLM you know the leading uh
language models how how do you score
them where do they run in terms of
fidelity do to um
>> well so in order to like score them so
to speak you have to have what we call
in the industry eval which is basically
like like question answer pairs where
you have like a question and then you
have like the right answer and you need
to compile a lot of those and so that's
something we've been working really hard
on is to kind of build the most
comprehensive uh eval set for for for
fidelity because and essentially this is
just because we need to do this in order
to effectively make mag workm Mhm.
>> We use um state-of-the-art models under
the hood.
>> Um namely because these state-of-the-art
models generally every every new model
that ships is just better at reasoning.
I I say that with quotation marks, just
smarter and it's therefore it's also
better at instruct following. So it
follows our instructions more
faithfully. And this is obviously
critically important like like don't
make something up if you don't have a
source like don't don't hallucinate.
>> Um so so we and we we always want our
our matter users to be able to take
advantage of the most cutting edge
models and that way they don't have it's
not a trade-off. like if they want the
smartest models, they don't have to they
don't have to abandon matters from the
eye and and go to like chatbt because
those models tend to be used under the
hood. We just have a whole bunch of
knowledge and orchestration on top of
that um to make the model even better at
being faithful, right? Um, so anyway,
this this is this is this is a long way
of saying it's uh it's it's a it's a
complicated uh process, but it's um and
and I and I but I think it's it's
essential that whenever we're using uh
when the church is is building Catholic
AI that we we can't we don't want to
have like a ghettoized approach where we
feel that in order to have a Catholic
AI, it means that we have to do it from
scratch ourselves, right? Because
essentially what it means is we won't
have as smart we won't have as good AI
and then and and then users will feel
compelled to go use you know secular
AIs. I mean so and this so this is not
to say that the the project of training
a Catholic language model is not worth
it. I mean it it is we we we have
effectively you know trained the world's
first Catholic language model called
Ephraim. uh we're now on on version two
of Ephraim and that project was
enormously helpful to us and I and I I
think it holds a lot of promise and it
could be in you know six to eight months
we will release that model to the world
for people to test and I think it'll be
I think it'll be impressive. Um, so I
think that, you know, trying to train a
a Catholic model is is is a worthy
endeavor, but uh for the foreseeable
future, given the pace of AI, it just
makes sense to to try and be AI
complete, right? Which is which is
effectively uh a way of saying uh uh
building a system which allows you to
leverage frontier state-of-the-art
capabilities uh with within your system.
And so your AI is as intelligent as it
possibly can be. And Matthew, what is
what is the hardest, you know, part of
of of, you know, working on this problem
of of of building and scaling Catholic
AI? What?
>> Well, I I I think the hardest part is
just um dealing with the fact that, you
know, this is about people's souls,
right? And and so that's it's it's a
it's a terrible responsibility. One that
um again like I I never like truly
appreciated when we started this
project. It was more of a kind of a
curiosity to us. I I never I never
thought we'd be going this deep into it.
It would scale so quickly. So, we take
that responsibility very seriously,
which is why we really value the
relationships we have um with with the
church, you know, more formally. Uh you
know, as I mentioned, we have a
scholarly advisory board, which has been
enormously helpful. We've we've worked
in collaborations, you know, basically
since the very beginning with Pontif
universities, notably the Pontifico
oriental Institute and now the
Pontiffical Gorian University in this
project. And again, without their help,
I I don't think I would have had the
confidence to proceed in this. So, I I
would say that I think generally is is
is the hardest thing is just um ensuring
that we're we're always especially when
we're when we're testing a new model
that we want to use, making sure we're
effectively evaluating that model
faithfully. Do we understand the way the
models are weak and and the way the
models are strong? And
>> and then really making sure that we can
mitigate the weaknesses before deploying
the model to ensure we don't lead anyone
astray. So, so that that's that's one of
the the the hardest problems is the the
the other the other uh I think the hard
problem is is just recognizing that you
know there are AIs out there which um
are doing are very useful and are great
and people appreciate and there are AIs
out there that are not great and are
leading people astray. I mean there are
AIs which are helping facilitate human
flourishing and there are AIs which are
actively I think in some ways impeding
you know flourishing. I mean, one one
example, not to pick on them because
it's not entirely fair, but like
character AI. We've heard like we've all
probably heard stories of people that,
you know, they end up they're becoming
their friends and they fall in love
>> with their character, a character AI,
and that's obviously like not good. Um,
>> and and so those AIs tend to give a kind
of a bad name to to the technology in
general. And so that becomes something
that we have to, you know, respond to.
Um so I I think you know one of the the
challenges just effectively educating
people about um what is what is the
technology what are its strengths what
are weaknesses what are the risks what
what are the possible rewards and just
ensuring people understand it so that
way they they leverage the tool um
effectively and and you know in as
responsible way as possible
>> and Matthew um I know you've been
traveling a lot you've been visiting
different bishop's conferences um
speaking with with the ley with with the
with the clergy um what have you learned
when speaking to them about about their
concerns or where they're at in terms of
adoption and also what are the things
that you you've brought back in terms of
of informing the work the research that
the team is doing? Well, I mean, one
thing that's given me a lot of hope is
initially, and I think I've said this
before, but when I initially went to
visit the bishious conferences to talk
about kind of kind of a basically the
trajectory of AI, but specifically what
we're doing in Catholic AI, I was
nervous like I I kind of felt like the
technology was very new and there was a
lot of controversy around it and I I
wasn't sure how it' be regarded. But for
the most part, I've been I've been um I
I've been very like pleasantly
surprised. I I think there's just it's
really for the most part I think that
there's a recognition now amongst the
bishops that this techn is not going
anywhere
>> and and it is a very powerful tool. It's
and it's too powerful for the church to
ignore. Kind of like the printing press,
right? I mean it would be absurd. I
mean, think of how far we come with the
printing press. Not to say that it
wasn't disruptive and cause some issues
as well, but certainly it's we're all
glad that the church embraced the
printing press. And I think I think in
the same way we're kind of at the same
point. It's uh AI can be used for good,
can be used for bad, but it's still
primarily a tool. Maybe not a neutral
tool as long as it's relying on heavily
on human data. And Pope Francis is
aligned on this, but it is still a tool,
a tool that can with if wielded
effectively can um be incredible for for
the for advancing things like
evangelization. And so I think right now
there's just a lot of confusion about
what the technology is, how it's going
to affect, you know, society, and and
what is the role for the church in
effectively leveraging this technology.
And I and I feel for the most part it's
just been especially amongst the bishops
it's just been curiosity. Um they want
to better understand the technology and
so that they can you know obviously
pastorally respond. And I think that's
kind of where we're at now is a
recognition we we have to use the
technology now. How do we provide the
right pastoral um direction and
instruction to uh to our priest and and
to the lady
>> and uh Matthew um you know of course the
the leader of the Catholic Church uh
Pope Leo I 14th uh famously took um he's
referenced this he's took his name in
you know in honor and in reflection of
of the work of Pope Leo I 13th who of
course shephered the church shephered
the faithful through another you know
transition revolution the industrial one
um we're obviously in an AI revolution
what Um, what are your hopes for his
papacy? And also, if you had the
opportunity to advise or or or speak
with him, what would you where would you
want him to turn his attention in terms
of of of shephering the the people of
God?
>> Well, thank God he's got a lot smarter
people advising him than me. So, I
expect he's getting very good advice and
and and uh and therefore won't have to
rely on mine. Um, but naturally, uh, I
do have a I do have, you know, some
feelings on this. I mean, and I think
I've talked about it a little bit. I've
kind of hinted at it earlier. uh perhaps
but I I think there there'll be some
people around him who want the pope to
use his office to try and encourage
companies to slow and you know companies
and countries to slow down the
technology to give people time to adapt
and to ensure that we have effective
regulation in place and that we can come
up with the right ethical frameworks and
and I certainly would understand why
they'd advise that but
my my insight would be we tried that and
if it's failed and I don't think that
the pope is going to make much of a
difference here and and like I said in
large part because uh of this kind of
China US
>> um this cold war that that's here that
they they neither side feels they can
effectively afford to lose. So I think
investing a lot of time and energy in
that is not very helpful. So that that
being said, I think it's very important
for the church to h have a official
position on on how the technology is
used in innumerable domains, right? And
to be very clear um that the technology
um being developed should always be be
focused on accelerating human
flourishing, not impeding it, right? So
and and so that that doesn't mean
necessarily that the technology um being
further developed means that nobody can
lose their jobs, right? Right. But it's
effectively it means that if people are
going to have to transition out of their
jobs to make to make room for for this
technology, those people should be taken
care of and have a a place to go and and
they should feel that there's there's
still work for them to do and that they
matter. So I think that's very very
important. I think so that that
obviously should be a very important
focus of of the pope and of course it
will be the but the area that I think is
like I I said before is most important
for the for the pope I think to focus on
and I I'm I think we're very fortunate.
I mean, I think it's providential that
we have an Augustinian
>> pope. It's just helping humanity to get
clear about what this whole civilization
project is supposed to be about. Like,
how do we build the city of God right on
on earth? And what what should the city
of God look like, feel like? What would
it be like to to experience a day in the
life of people living in this in the
city of God? It's really important that
we get clear clear about that.
>> I can't I can't express that enough. Um,
you know, I think in the past there
there have been shows, I know the show
is not perfect, but you know, Star Trek
Next Generation is a good example,
right? Where it showed a vision of
humanity where we'd beaten poverty,
right? We'd overcome racism and greed
and humanity was now focused on
exploring the stars and and apparently,
you know, as they say in the show, Earth
was kind of like paradise, right? And
and that that was very hopeful. It's a
hopeful sign that we can do this, right?
And so it showed some kind of vision of
the future. And then in principle, I
know that that inspired people like
Trekies, right, to say like that's it. I
want to be part of that human project
and so I'm going to dedicate my life to
to trying to emulate the values that
they live by and I want to try and build
that kind of world. Well, I kind of
think we need that now. Like we need to
have that kind of we need to have that
kind of concrete vision of the future
and and and for no other reason. Um I I
I would say we won't be able to
effectively regulate the technology
unless we have um a clear sense for how
we want the technology to be developed
and what problems we should be pointing
it at. I mean like when you're
regulating it, you're saying, you know,
the technology should be used in this
way, but it shouldn't be used in that
way, you know, effectively. Well, then
how do we make that that credential
determination that's based on some
understanding of what the human person's
about, what civilization's about, right?
And so we have to have some sense of
ideally what what people should be doing
with their time and energies and and and
how civilization is should be built in
order to help facilitate, you know,
human flourishing. And I think we're not
clear about that at all. So, I think
there's there's a there's a I think
there's a real chance of a bunch of
different interests getting involved.
Um, you know, have very specific ideas
about how the technology developed. And
I'm not saying that those ideas are
always going to be bad, but I they may
not always be consistent. And so, I
think that the pope just needs needs to
remind us of of what human life is
supposed to be about, what civilization
is supposed to be all about, and what
we, as I said before, should be paddling
towards. And I think if he can
effectively do that, that would be
enormously beneficial not just for the
church, but actually for the AI industry
itself. I mean, even the heads of the AI
labs, I mean, this is something that
that they're cons. They have kids like
many of those those founders. So, they
they're worried about the future and
they want to show the technology
directed to the right places and they
want effective regulation, ensure that
it's developed, you know, uh well, and
and to ensure that the transition to the
new AI and robotics age is done
peacefully and doesn't leave people
behind. Um but that requires vision and
and I think that's that's one thing that
we we we seriously lack nowadays.
>> And uh Matthew, a final question here is
um the goal, you know, our goal should
be to become saints. Um that's that's
the goal of every Catholic. Um how would
the saints use AI? I mean it's it's has
the potential, you know, you mentioned
this the new evangelization. It has the
potential to to change the way we we
operate, the way we think. Potentially
we'll have a lot more time on our hands.
Of course, the internet has allowed us
to communicate with everyone in the
world. Um, how how do you see the, you
know, in in our tradition of the great
saints, how would they how would they
utilize this moment in time?
>> Well, I mean, I think back to when I was
a seminarian and I remember, you know, I
I I just come out of the army and here I
was studying philosophy and theology,
right? And and I like I I did not feel
ready for this or um or even really
capable in some ways. And I remember
walking into the library at our seminary
and just looking at all the books being
like, "Oh man, I what have I got myself
into here?" Right? And and I and I, you
know, and it was it was it was not easy,
right? If I had a question that I wanted
answered, I you know, um sometimes you
could talk to a librarian, they could
point you to a few books and then you'd
go to this this card indexes and you
know, you you talk to your professors
and get some suggestions and you try and
find books that that make sense and then
you go to the books, you pull the books
out of the stacks. I know this for the
younger generation, this must seem
crazy. you pull the book out and you
have to kind of read skim through the
book to see uh if it speaks to the
particular you know area that you're
you're you're doing research into. Um it
was tedious and took forever. I mean it
took took a long time and and I think
today if I I think today like with
matter effectively what's happening here
it's it's like the analogy I like to use
it's like walking into that library
and and shouting out your question to
the library and then all of a sudden the
books just start popping off the
shelves, right? and they and they and
they're like they float over to you and
they just open right to the exact page
with with the answer that you're looking
for just like that, right? I mean,
that's kind of what AI is. Um it it
allows us to to take everything that the
saints have said, everything the church
has said and and allow the the insights
which are most important to us, most
value to us, and allow those to be
brought forward and and be made useful
like to me to to be able to apply them
to my life. And if I think of like for
the saints, right? um if they had this
this technology um I I mean I think they
would have been over the moon. I think
it would have been for Thomas Aquinus I
think his mind would have just blown
right. I mean what an opportunity. Never
before in the history of humanity
has has any person really in anywhere in
the world anyone with who has internet
access the internet can effectively like
through Madison right now access at
least you know the official the entire
body the official all of church teaching
and and all they have to do is ask and
and and that the church teaching which
is relevant will be distilled down for
them and and made applicable. This is
incredible. This is this is absolutely
incredible. And this is why I think it
it's probably the greatest unlock for
the new evangelization that we've ever
experienced. And we we already seen that
on the platform. You know, people come
sometimes they're not we we know they're
not Catholic and and they're hitting the
AI, you know, with what the world's told
them the church believes and then they
they get they get into this dialogue
with the AI and then they slowly start
to understand that some of those ideas
were not right. Right. And then they
they they they basically just they jump
in the rabbit hole, right? And next
thing you know, um they've been
intellectually converted, right? they're
kind of ready to take that next next
step in their faith journey. I mean,
this is incredible. 24 hours a day,
seven days a week, it's working with,
you know, tens of thousands of people
around the world to answer their
questions and and people are are are
making these journeys effectively
without without even, you know, in some
cases talking to a Catholic, which is a
problem in some that's not sufficient.
It's not an end of itself. Obviously,
it's incredibly important that we we
learn how to effectively offer people so
that they can engage the the the church
communities, they can they can find a
good parish, they can find a good priest
and um but but it but I think for
recognizing that we do have a priest
shortage and there's not there's not
enough uh lelay Catholic ministers out
there and that people are on the
internet um browsing around me, I think
it's it's it's uh it's incredible to me
that they now have a place they can go
to dialogue with basically what all the
saints have said that that's incredible.
So I'm very obviously I'm very bullish
on the technology and I think it's it
definitely I think is certainly the
greatest unlock for the new evangelation
which is why we have to really double
down on this technology and ensure that
we're we're we're building it in such a
way that can it can truly meet people
where they're at.
>> Well, Matthew, this has been incredibly
inspiring and uh we look forward to to
you know maximizing and using
Magisterium AI for that great
evangelization that is ahead of us.
>> Thanks for the conversation. Thank you.